Email: joel.middleton@gmail.com

Phone: (202) 431-1412

Personal site: https://joelmidd.github.io/

SUMMARY

My academic research has developed a flexible statistics framework for the analysis of virtually any experimental design, even those for which no existing analytical results are available due to setting-specific research constraints, complex assignment dependencies or interference. Complementing this research, I have 18 years' experience implementing field experiments in challenging contexts, such as political campaigns or conflict zones, and in modeling voter behavior for political organizations. I also have extensive professional experience designing and analyzing surveys, with expertise in item construction and testing, probability sampling, experimental survey design, and data analysis.

ACADEMIC POSITIONS

2014- Assistant Professor, Department of Political Science

University of California, Berkeley

2011-2014 Visiting Assistant Professor, Department of Applied Statistics, Social Science and Humanities

Affiliations:

- Center for Data Science and Center

- Center for the Promotion of Research Involving Innovative Statistical Methodology

New York University

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

2001-2018 Consulting Statistician. Penn, Schoen and Berland Associates

Designed and implemented: machine learning models of voter behavior for statewide voter outreach campaigns; survey experiments using optimal, fractional or factorial designs.

2008-2009 Senior Analyst. Analyst Institute

Designed and implemented: large-scale voter targeting models and models of voter behavior; field experiments evaluating impact of voter outreach and mobilization; research in challenging campaign environments with novel designs that address field-constraints; research

dissemination.

2001-2005 Consultant II. The Rendon Group

Oversaw budgets, designed research and managed analysts for DARPA-funded research. Designed and implemented media coding protocols for quantitative measurement of news content from 40 countries worldwide. Trained eleven foreign language analysts in media

coding protocols and oversaw quality control.

1999-2001 Statistician. Penn, Schoen and Berland Associates

Designed and implemented: survey experiments using optimal, fractional or factorial designs;

interactive simulation tools; survey instruments.

Joel A. Middleton, PhD Assistant Professor of Political Science University of California, Berkeley Email: joel.middleton@gmail.com

Phone: (202) 431-1412

Personal site: https://joelmidd.github.io/

EDUCATION

2011	Doctor of Philosophy in Political Science Yale University
2004	Master of Science in Statistics The George Washington University
1999	Master of Science in Psychology Brown University
1997	Bachelor of Science in Psychology Lewis and Clark College

RESEARCH: CAUSAL INFERENCE/DESIGN-BASED INFERENCE (DBI)

- A Design-based Theory of Optimal Index Construction *Working paper* **2022**, with A Demin and C Samii
- A Unified Approach to Evaluating Estimators in Complex Experimental Designs *Working paper* **2022**, with H Chang
- How to Account for Alternatives When Comparing Effects: Revisiting 'Bringing Education to Afghan Girls' *arXiv:2106.15076* **2022**, with D Burde, R Rahnama, and C Samii
- Optimized Variance Estimation under Interference and Complex Experimental Designs arXiv:2112.01709 **2021**, with C Harshaw, and F Sävje
- Unifying DBI: A New Variance Estimation Principle *arXiv:2109.09236* **2021**
- Unifying DBI: On Estimating the Variance of Linear Estimators in any Experimental Design *arXiv*:2109.09220 **2021**
- Exact Bias Correction for Linear Adjustment of Randomized Controlled Trials arXiv:2110.08425 2021, with H Chang and P M Aronow
- A Unified Theory of Regression Adjustment for Design-based Inference arXiv:1803.06011 2018
- Potential for Bias Inflation with Grouped Data: A Comparison of Estimators and Sensitivity Analysis Strategy *Observational Studies* **2018**, with M Scott, R Diakow, and J Hill
- Bias Amplification and Bias Unmasking *Political Analysis* **2017**, **24(3)**: **307-323**, with J Hill and M Scott
- A Class of Unbiased Estimators of the Average Treatment Effect in Randomized Experiments Journal of Causal Inference 2013, 1(1): 135–154, with P M Aronow
- Unbiased Estimation of the Average Treatment Effect in Cluster Randomized Experiments *Statistics, Politics and Policy* **2015**, **1: 39-75**, with P M Aronow

Joel A. Middleton, PhD Assistant Professor of Political Science University of California, Berkeley Email: joel.middleton@gmail.com

Phone: (202) 431-1412

Personal site: https://joelmidd.github.io/

Bias of the Regression Estimator for Experiments Using Clustered Random Assignment *Statistics and Probability Letters* **2008**, **78**: **2654–2659**

RESEARCH: EXPERIMENTS AND QUASI-EXPERIMENTS

Can Communities Take Charge? A Randomized Controlled Trial on Sustaining Schools in Afghanistan *Working paper* **2022**, with D Burde, C Samii and Y Wang

Can Foreign Aid Boost State Legitimacy During Conflict? Experimental Evidence from Afghanistan *Working paper* **2022**, with D Burde, R Deitz, and C Samii

Political Communication: Insights from Field Experiments

Oxford Handbook of Political Communication 2017, 1-15, with D P Green and A Carnegie

Are Ballot Initiative Outcomes Influenced by Independent Groups? A Precinct-Randomized Experiment *Political Behavior* **2015**, **37(3)**: **1-27**, with T Rogers

Priming Under Fire: Reverse Causality and the Classic Media Priming Hypothesis *Journal of Politics* **2014**, **76(2)**: **581-592**, with A Hart

Do Community-Based Voter Mobilization Campaigns Work Even in Battleground States? Evaluating the Effectiveness of MoveOn's 2004 Outreach Campaign *Quarterly Journal of Political Science* **2008**, **3**: **63–82**, with D P Green

POLICY PAPERS

Assessment of Learning Outcomes and Social Effects of Community-Based Education: A Randomized Field Experiment in Afghanistan. *New York University*, with D Burde, and C. Samii

Reports:

- Phase Two Endline Report. 2019, also with M Lisiecki and O Okhidoi
- Phase Two Baseline Report. 2018
- Phase One Outcomes Report. 2016
- Phase One Baseline Report. 2015

Briefs:

- Can Communities Take Charge? Sustainability and CBE. 2019, 3(3)
- Capacity Building for Village Level Community Institutions. 2018, 3(2)
- Enhancing Female Representation in the Education Sector. 2018, 3(1)
- Teacher Motivations and Implications for Models of Community-based Education. 2017, 2(4)
- Institutional Management Practices of Village Shuras in Rural Afghanistan. 2017, 2(3)
- Community Capacity to Co-manage Primary Education. 2017, 2(2)
- Community Participation and the Sustainability of Rural Schools in Afghanistan. 2017, 2(1)
- Prioritizing Community-based Education Resources by Age Groups. 2016, 1(4)
- Evaluating the Trade-Offs in Teacher Recruitment. 2016, 1(3)
- Cost-Effectiveness Analysis. 2016, 1(2)
- Community-Based Education in Afghanistan: A Primer. 2016, 1(1)

Email: joel.middleton@gmail.com

Phone: (202) 431-1412

Personal site: https://joelmidd.github.io/

GRANTS	5
--------	---

2014-2017	Awarded: \$7.2 million. Co-PI with Cyrus Samii, and Dana Burde, PI. Title: Social Effects and Learning Outcomes from Community-based Education: A Randomized Field Experiment in Afghanistan. <i>United States Agency for International Development</i> (USAID)
2013	Awarded: \$250,000. Co-PI with Dana Burde, PI. Title: Social Effects and Learning Outcomes from Community-based Education: A Randomized Field Experiment in Afghanistan. <i>Danish International Development Agency</i>
2013	Awarded: \$17,833. Co-PI with Dana Burde, PI. Title: Community-based Schools and Trust in Government: A Randomized Field Experiment in Afghanistan. <i>Institute for Human Development and Social Change</i>

CONFERENCES AND INVITED TALKS

2020	UC Berkeley Economics Seminar. Invited talk. Unifying Design-based Inference: Variance Estimation
2019	UC Berkeley Research Workshop in American Politics. Invited talk. Index Construction
2018	American Political Science Association. Talk. Exactly Unbiased Regression Adjustment
2018	Society for Political Methodology. Talk. A Unified Theory of Regression Adjustment for Design-based Inference
2018	UC Berkeley Causal Inference Seminar. Invited talk. A Unified Theory of Regression Adjustment for Design-based Inference
2017	Association for Analytical Learning about Islam and Muslim Societies. Talk. Bringing Education to Afghan Girls Revisited: Understanding When and Why Effects Vary
2016	Yale International Methods Workshop. Invited talk. Estimation Approaches for Rerandomized Designs
2016	Harris School Political Economy Workshop. Invited talk. Bias Amplification and Bias Unmasking
2016	Midwest Political Science Association. Talk. Bias Amplification and Bias Unmasking
2016	Society for Political Methodology. Poster. Design-based Inference for Complex Experimental Designs
2015	Joint Statistical Meetings. Talk. Bias Amplification in Context: The Case of Fixed Effects
2015	Joint Statistical Meetings. Talk. Bias Amplification Bounds
2015	Stanford Political Methods Workshop. Invited talk. Bias Amplification and Bias Unmasking

Joel A. Middleton, PhD Assistant Professor of Political Science University of California, Berkeley Email: joel.middleton@gmail.com

Phone: (202) 431-1412

Personal site: https://joelmidd.github.io/

2013	Joint Statistical Meetings. Talk. Inclusion/Exclusion Criteria for Bias Amplifying Covariates: A Sensitivity Analysis Framework
2013	Joint Statistical Meetings. Talk. Shrinkage for Improved Inference in High Dimensional Factorial Experiment on Voter Mobilization
2011	Midwest Political Science Association. Talk. Direct-Mail Campaigns Can Persuade Voters: Evidence from a Randomized Field Experiment Studying Ballot Guides in Oregon
2011	Analyst Group Meeting. Invited talk. Priming, Projection or Both: Reevaluating the Classic Media Priming Hypothesis
2009	Society for Political Methodology. Poster. What Characteristics Must an Omitted Variable Have to Bias an Estimator by a Given Amount?
2008	Society for Political Methodology. Poster. Is Matching Really "Essential" for Cluster Randomized Experiments?

TEACHING

Department of Political Science, University of California, Berkeley

- Quantitative Analysis in Political Research (PS 231A)
- Design-based Causal Inference (PS 239)
- Research Workshop in Quantitative Modeling (PS 291F)
- Public Opinion and Voting (PS 161)

Department of Applied Statistics, Social Science and Humanities, New York University

- Survey Research Methods (RESCH-GE 2139)
- Large Databases in Education Research (E10.2110)
- Introductory Statistics (RESCH-GE 1085)

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

2016-present	Member, Experiments in Governance and Politics (EGAP)
2019	Graduate Admissions Committee, UC Berkeley
2017	Coordinator for Research Workshop in American Politics, UC Berkeley
2014-2015	Editor, Statistics, Politics and Policy
2011-2013	Committee on Statistics Education, PRIISM Center, New York University
2011	Survey Methods Consultant, CARE International